<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Training Set</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2016 18:41:51 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2016 18:41:51 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Changes in Baltimore Neighborhood Policing</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;With the massive change in Baltimore Police Department arrests in 2015 I thought it might be worth investigating how each neighborhood was affected.  Thankfully it appears the &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.baltimorecity.gov/Public-Safety/BPD-Arrests/3i3v-ibrt&quot;&gt;BPD arrest dataset on Open Baltimore&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://bniajfi.org&quot;&gt;Baltimore Neighborhood Indicators Alliance “Vital Signs” composite dataset&lt;/a&gt; use the same Census neighborhood definitions so we can look at the arrest rates in each neighborhood as it relates to the population and demograhpics.  I’ve mapped two indicators by neighbohood that you can toggle between: the percent change in the number of arrests from 2014 to 2015 and the change in the arrest rate per 1,000 people in each neighbohood from 2014 to 2015.  I’ve only included neighborhoods with more than 200 people in the population to try and remove some of the (numerically) noisier neighborhoods.  Like I mentioned in the &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/16/Marijuana-Policy-Only-Part-of-Drop-in-Arrests&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, these changes are not all directly tied to the change in marijuana policy; indeed it would be hard to imagine 10,000 fewer arrests in Baltimore, a drop of about 29%, due to marijuana policy alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Select&lt;/strong&gt; from the “Visible Layers” in the upper right corner which layer you want to view.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Hover&lt;/strong&gt; over each neighborhood to get the arrest counts from 2013, 2014, and 2015.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Click&lt;/strong&gt; on a neighborhood to get additional statistics about the arrests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;width:90%;&quot;&gt;  
&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;520&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;https://jtelszasz.cartodb.com/viz/cb985822-b92b-11e5-9421-0ecd1babdde5/embed_map&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general the neighborhoods with higher arrest rates to begin with stood to experience larger changes in 2015.  For example, in 2013, &lt;strong&gt;Freddie Gray’s neighborhood of Sandtown-Windchester&lt;/strong&gt; on the near west side had an &lt;strong&gt;arrest rate of more than 100 arrests per 1,000 people&lt;/strong&gt;.  That number in 2015 is now about 57 arrests per 1,000 people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;monthly-totals&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;monthly-totals&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/images/2016-02/Total_Monthly_Arrests_2014_2015.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Monthly total arrests in Baltimore, 2015 in orange. &lt;a href=&quot;/images/2016-02/Total_Monthly_Arrests_2014_2015.png&quot;&gt;Click here to enlarge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;The big changes in arrest numbers could be good or bad - if the drop was because of abandoning a stop-and-frisk or broken windows-type policing approach in lieu of fairer community policing tactics I think we could live with that.  I’m not convinced that’s the case, especially considering Freddie Gray was arrested and died in police custody well after the slow down had begun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a more methodical look at these changes in Baltimore, here are the number of Baltimore neighborhoods by their change in arrest rate.  Again, total arrests in Baltimore dropped by about 29% between 2014 and 2015.  The mean for the neighborhoods is slightly different (about 20% drop) because I’ve excluded neighborhoods with less than 200 people in the population.  Some neighborhoods with more than that population have very small arrest counts (Roland Park, Guilford) so those are the ones that have 200% or 300% increases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;fullwidth&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2016-02/Histogram - Percent Change in Arrests by Nhood.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The average Baltimore neighborhood saw about 14 arrests fewer per 1,000 people in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;fullwidth&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2016-02/Histogram - Change in Arrest Rate by Nhood.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;width: 100%; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;

BPD arrests data obtained from &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.baltimorecity.gov/&quot;&gt;Open Baltimore&lt;/a&gt;, data downloaded January 7, 2016.&lt;br /&gt;

Thanks as always to &lt;a href=&quot;http://bniajfi.org&quot;&gt;BNIA-JFI&lt;/a&gt; for compiling the &quot;Vital Signs&quot; indicators for Baltimore.&lt;br /&gt;

Analysis conducted using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.python.org&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandas.pydata.org&quot;&gt;Pandas&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.qgis.org&quot;&gt;QGIS&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cartodb.com&quot;&gt;CartoDB&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;

Analysis Jupyter (iPython) notebooks can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jtelszasz/baltimore_crime/blob/master/neighborhood_arrest_changes.ipynb&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;

QGIS project and shapefiles can also be found on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jtelszasz/baltimore_crime&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
  (function(i,s,o,g,r,a,m){i[&#39;GoogleAnalyticsObject&#39;]=r;i[r]=i[r]||function(){
  (i[r].q=i[r].q||[]).push(arguments)},i[r].l=1*new Date();a=s.createElement(o),
  m=s.getElementsByTagName(o)[0];a.async=1;a.src=g;m.parentNode.insertBefore(a,m)
  })(window,document,&#39;script&#39;,&#39;//www.google-analytics.com/analytics.js&#39;,&#39;ga&#39;);

  ga(&#39;create&#39;, &#39;UA-58835878-1&#39;, &#39;auto&#39;);
  ga(&#39;send&#39;, &#39;pageview&#39;);

&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/16/Changes-In-Neighborhood-Policing</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/16/Changes-In-Neighborhood-Policing</guid>
        
        <category>Baltimore</category>
        
        <category>marijuana</category>
        
        <category>police</category>
        
        
        <category>articles</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Maryland Marijuana Policy Only Accounts for 17% of Drop in Baltimore Arrests</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When looking at Baltimore Police Department (BPD) arrest statistics it’s important to note that in Maryland possession of less than 10 grams of marijuana is no longer grounds for arrest, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/local/md-politics/maryland-senate-expected-to-take-vote-on-decriminalizing-marijuana/2014/03/14/ca64eb28-ab22-11e3-98f6-8e3c562f9996_story.html?tid=a_inl&quot;&gt;effective October 1, 2014&lt;/a&gt;.  When looking at the drop in arrests from 2014 to 2015 we can at least expect to attribute a portion of the drop to the change in marijuana policy.  But exactly how much? &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fewer-arrests-in-2015&quot;&gt;10,616 fewer arrests in 2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;marijuana-totals&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;marijuana-totals&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/images/2016-02/Totals Marijuana.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thetrainingset.com/articles/15/Policing-In-Baltimore-In-2015&quot;&gt;My previous estimate&lt;/a&gt; was that we’d finish the year with about 10,000 fewer arrests in Baltimore in 2015 compared to 2014.  The final tally is shown at right, indicating the &lt;strong&gt;drop between 2014 and 2015 was 10,616&lt;/strong&gt;, or a 28.8% decrease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marijuana-related arrests have been declining since 2013, falling from 13.6% of all arrests to just under 2%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;policy-change-effect-on-arrests&quot;&gt;Policy change effect on arrests&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of the 10,616 fewer arrests in 2015, what portion are due to the drop in marijuana arrests?  Looking at all marijuana-related arrests, the number is about 25.9%.  Looking at only the charge for possession of less than 10 grams (which is the charge that we should see practically zero of in 2015 due to the policy change), the portion is only about 17%.  (There were about 1,812 fewer arrests for this charge in 2015 which is about 17% of the 10,616 fewer total arrests.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2016-02/Marijuana Breakouts.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is of course only the arrests for which possession of 10 grams of marijuana was the charge.  I’m guessing that possession of marijuana used to be the open door for police to nab people for other offenses (or potentially trump up charges).  So while only 17% is directly attributable, a larger portion of the drop in arrests might be attributed indirectly to the change in marijuana policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;width: 100%; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;

BPD arrests data obtained from &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.baltimorecity.gov/&quot;&gt;Open Baltimore&lt;/a&gt;, data downloaded January 7, 2016.&lt;br /&gt;

Analysis conducted using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.python.org&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandas.pydata.org&quot;&gt;Pandas&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.plot.ly&quot;&gt;Plot.ly&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;

Full analysis Jupyter (iPython) notebook can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jtelszasz/baltimore_crime/blob/master/marijuana.ipynb&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
  (function(i,s,o,g,r,a,m){i[&#39;GoogleAnalyticsObject&#39;]=r;i[r]=i[r]||function(){
  (i[r].q=i[r].q||[]).push(arguments)},i[r].l=1*new Date();a=s.createElement(o),
  m=s.getElementsByTagName(o)[0];a.async=1;a.src=g;m.parentNode.insertBefore(a,m)
  })(window,document,&#39;script&#39;,&#39;//www.google-analytics.com/analytics.js&#39;,&#39;ga&#39;);

  ga(&#39;create&#39;, &#39;UA-58835878-1&#39;, &#39;auto&#39;);
  ga(&#39;send&#39;, &#39;pageview&#39;);

&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/16/Marijuana-Policy-Only-Part-of-Drop-in-Arrests</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/16/Marijuana-Policy-Only-Part-of-Drop-in-Arrests</guid>
        
        <category>Baltimore</category>
        
        <category>marijuana</category>
        
        <category>police</category>
        
        
        <category>articles</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Two Way Streets: Parking on St. Paul and Calvert</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Baltimore Department of Transportation is toying with the idea of converting St. Paul and Calvert streets to two-way traffic.  These streets are components of a north-south corridor that bring northern Baltimore and Baltimore County residents directly into the heart of the city.  &lt;!--more--&gt;Based on Baltimore Brew’s reporting the response at even exploring the notion has been negative&lt;label for=&quot;brew-meetings&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;brew-meetings&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;See Baltimore Brew articles on DOT’s three meetings &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.baltimorebrew.com/2015/11/19/one-way-or-two-for-st-paul-and-calvert-streets/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.baltimorebrew.com/2015/12/02/doomsday-scenario-described-if-st-paul-and-calvert-streets-are-converted-to-two-way-traffic/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.baltimorebrew.com/2015/12/10/anxiety-about-two-way-street-conversion-and-frustration-with-city-life/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;. Frankly, I had no earthly idea so many in Baltimore City were clairvoyant, though I have no choice but to concede this is the case what with the adamant declarations that two-way conversion for these streets will simply never work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;on-two-way-complete-streets&quot;&gt;On two-way complete streets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My understanding of the urban planning literature of late is that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.governing.com/topics/transportation-infrastructure/The-Return-of-the.html&quot;&gt;conversion to two-way complete streets&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.citylab.com/cityfixer/2015/07/the-many-benefits-of-making-one-way-streets-two-way/398960/&quot;&gt;supports business, improves safety, and makes for a generally more lively neighborhood&lt;/a&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;two-way-eff&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;two-way-eff&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Not to mention that two-way streets may make for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.accessmagazine.org/articles/fall-2012/two-way-street-networks-efficient-previously-thought/&quot;&gt;more efficient within-network travel&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thoroughfares with high vehicle throughputs, on the other hand, tend to bifurcate communities.  We don’t have to look any farther than Baltimore itself - Orleans provides direct access from downtown to Johns Hopkins but destroys any sense of a livable community along that dangerous corridor.  I-83, a federal interstate that reaches from the northern suburbs into the downtown heart of Baltimore, forms a clear demarcation between Mt. Vernon/downtown and East Baltimore.  Even the now upper middle class (read: yuppie) neighborhood of Canton would do well to slow Boston street and make it more pedestrian friendly - as it stands, you still have to get in a car to get to the Target or the restaurants on the waterfront.  Despite thriving business it isn’t exactly a pedestrian friendly corridor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;speeding&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;speeding&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Perhaps worth noting here that the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.baltimoresun.com/news/maryland/baltimore-city/bs-md-ci-speed-camera-council-20150601-story.html&quot;&gt;defunct red-light camera program&lt;/a&gt; in Baltimore didn’t include any intersections on the St. Paul/Calvert corridor, and though I have no data to support it I’ve never once seen any speeding enforcement on either of these streets, nor Baltimore in general. &lt;/span&gt; Perhaps economic activity isn’t the goal on St. Paul and Calvert - that’s largely left to North Charles St. a block west in terms of businesses - but a gentle 2% downhill grade from the north all the way to downtown and lights timed just poorly enough to encourage hitting the gas instead of the brake makes for regular 40 mph speedersflying through a residential neighborhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-look-at-parking-on-st-paul-and-calvert&quot;&gt;A look at parking on St. Paul and Calvert&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, I’m curious as to whether any of the public datasets from &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.baltimorecity.gov&quot;&gt;Open Baltimore&lt;/a&gt; can suggest a path forward.  One aspect that city-dwellers are sure to complain of in light of potential street changes is parking.  We can first take a look at the parking citation data I had dug into a while back.  &lt;label for=&quot;morethan10&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;morethan10&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Only blocks with ten or more citations are shown. &lt;/span&gt;Presented below are the total parking citations on these blocks between January 1, 2014 and November 30, 2015.  It’s probably no surprise that the areas near Johns Hopkins and University of Baltimore/Maryland Institute College of Art (part of a dense residential neighborhood) have particularly high citation counts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;width:90%;&quot;&gt;  
&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;520&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;https://jtelszasz.cartodb.com/viz/875acdb2-a7e1-11e5-8f59-0ecfd53eb7d3/embed_map&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total ticket counts for St. Paul and Calvert from January 1, 2014 through November 30, 2015 are practically equivalent: 19,500 tickets on St. Paul and 20,184 on Calvert.  20,000 citations over about 600 days is about 33 citations a day for each of these approximately three mile stretches of street - or about 10 citations per mile per day.  &lt;label for=&quot;enforcement&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;enforcement&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;It could be that one parking cop is making his or her way up Calvert from downtown and then down St. Paul. &lt;/span&gt;Judging by the hourly totals presented below, it appears that enforcement on St. Paul falls behind Calvert by about an hour or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Total parking citations by hour, January 1, 2014 through November 30, 2015.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015-12/st_paul_calvert_citations_hourly.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parking is just one aspect of the multi-faceted question of converting one-way streets to two-way.  It’s hard to read too much into these top-level data on citations without additional information, like how many actual parking spots are on each block, but the design would certainly have to consider what to do at each of these dense university spots.  My hope is that the &lt;a href=&quot;http://mta.maryland.gov/baltimorelink&quot;&gt;upcoming MTA bus route redesign&lt;/a&gt; will be integrated with these potential two-way conversions and will provide good alternatives to car dependency in Baltimore.  Especially for college kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bonus:&lt;/strong&gt; fun anecdote from one of the public meetings.  I attended the third of DOT’s public meeting on December 15.  A gentleman in a pinstripe suit graced us with his presence and personal tragedy.  Holding up two pictures, one of his office “with a beautiful view in downtown Baltimore” and the other, the neighboring office with similar view and being used, to his dismay, for storage, he claimed that “all” of his coworkers had moved out of Baltimore because it had conspired to make life difficult for them.  He was the last holdout of his cohort, bunkered in his perpetually under-siege residence in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=guilford+baltimore&amp;amp;source=lnms&amp;amp;tbm=isch&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwjO6aD20-_JAhVGOj4KHejQBJUQ_AUICSgD&amp;amp;biw=1196&amp;amp;bih=728&quot;&gt;Guilford&lt;/a&gt;.  Converting these streets to two-way, he claimed was the proverbial last straw (beyond paying “$9,000 in taxes and $20,000 a year to put [his] kids in private school”), and he’d be forced to once and for all move out of Baltimore.  Ignoring the fact that slowing traffic and building complete streets would actually benefit the residents on these streets, he was fed up with Baltimore’s personal attacks on his well being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His story is certainly at one end of the spectrum, but it at least points at the question of for whom cities and its infrastructure are designed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  (function(i,s,o,g,r,a,m){i[&#39;GoogleAnalyticsObject&#39;]=r;i[r]=i[r]||function(){
  (i[r].q=i[r].q||[]).push(arguments)},i[r].l=1*new Date();a=s.createElement(o),
  m=s.getElementsByTagName(o)[0];a.async=1;a.src=g;m.parentNode.insertBefore(a,m)
  })(window,document,&#39;script&#39;,&#39;//www.google-analytics.com/analytics.js&#39;,&#39;ga&#39;);

  ga(&#39;create&#39;, &#39;UA-58835878-1&#39;, &#39;auto&#39;);
  ga(&#39;send&#39;, &#39;pageview&#39;);

&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Dec 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/15/Parking-and-2-Way-Conversion</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/15/Parking-and-2-Way-Conversion</guid>
        
        <category>parking</category>
        
        <category>two-way-streets</category>
        
        <category>urban-planning</category>
        
        
        <category>articles</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fresh Style</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I decided it was time to freshen up things around here.  My new look is a mashup of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/clayh53/tufte-jekyll&quot;&gt;Tufte&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rosario/kasper&quot;&gt;Kasper&lt;/a&gt; themes for Jekyll.  I’m a fan of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.edwardtufte.com/tufte/&quot;&gt;Edward Tufte&lt;/a&gt;’s work and I think the layout gives more flexibility in presenting data and analysis.  It took quite a bit of time and tweaking and I’m sure I’ve broken some things but I’m happy with how it turned out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope you all dig the new look!  Let me know what you think or if you found something broken with a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/thetrainingset&quot;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt; or an &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#116;&amp;#104;&amp;#101;&amp;#116;&amp;#114;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#110;&amp;#105;&amp;#110;&amp;#103;&amp;#115;&amp;#101;&amp;#116;&amp;#064;&amp;#103;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#046;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&quot;&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  (function(i,s,o,g,r,a,m){i[&#39;GoogleAnalyticsObject&#39;]=r;i[r]=i[r]||function(){
  (i[r].q=i[r].q||[]).push(arguments)},i[r].l=1*new Date();a=s.createElement(o),
  m=s.getElementsByTagName(o)[0];a.async=1;a.src=g;m.parentNode.insertBefore(a,m)
  })(window,document,&#39;script&#39;,&#39;//www.google-analytics.com/analytics.js&#39;,&#39;ga&#39;);

  ga(&#39;create&#39;, &#39;UA-58835878-1&#39;, &#39;auto&#39;);
  ga(&#39;send&#39;, &#39;pageview&#39;);

&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/15/New-Style</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/15/New-Style</guid>
        
        <category>The-Training-Set</category>
        
        
        <category>articles</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Baltimore Policing: Six Months After Freddie Gray Events</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We’re about six months out now from the Freddie Gray incident and subsequent unrest in Baltimore.  There have been a few dominant narratives about crime in Baltimore since, namely that we’ve had almost &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.baltimoresun.com/bing-maps/homicides/index.php?show_results=UPDATE+MAP&amp;amp;range=2015&amp;amp;district=all&amp;amp;zipcode=All&amp;amp;cause=all&amp;amp;age=all&amp;amp;gender=all&amp;amp;race=all&amp;amp;article=all&quot;&gt;300 homicides&lt;/a&gt;, that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.baltimoresun.com/news/maryland/bs-md-ci-comstat-meeting-20150616-story.html&quot;&gt;police stopped doing their jobs after the protests&lt;/a&gt;, and that enough prescription drugs had flooded the streets to “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.baltimoresun.com/news/maryland/baltimore-riots/bal-drugs-on-baltimore-streets-could-keep-it-high-for-a-year-batts-says-20150604-story.html&quot;&gt;keep Baltimore high for a year&lt;/a&gt;.” &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what has actually gone on in Baltimore in the weeks and months since the spring of 2015?  I think there are a couple of important storylines in the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;precipitous-drop-in-police-productivity---on-track-for-10000-less-arrests-this-year-than-last&quot;&gt;Precipitous drop in police productivity - on track for 10,000 less arrests this year than last.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re on pace to record 10,000 less arrests this year compared to last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Monthly arrests in Baltimore for 2013, 2014, and 2015.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015-11/Total_Monthly_Arrests.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total arrests for 2013 and 2014 were both on the order of 36,000 and this year, looking at total records through September, it’s looking like it will be more like 26,000.  (The average daily arrests for January through September is extrapolated through the rest of the year.)  There’s a substantial downtick in arrests in the last quarter of the year for both 2013 and 2014 though, so the 26,000 number could in fact be high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Cumulative arrests in Baltimore for 2013, 2014, and 2015.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015-11/Total_Arrests_Cumsum.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This kind of output isn’t the result of a drastic change in the size of the police force either.  The number of officers for 2013, 2014, and 2015 are 2,316, 2,278, and 2,224 respectively, resulting in average annual arrests per officer going from just over 17, to just over 16, &lt;em&gt;down to 12 arrests per officer this year&lt;/em&gt;.  This means there had to have been a shift in policing tactics this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#39;http://localhost:4000/images/2015-11/Total_Arrests_Cumsum.png&#39;&gt;&lt;img src=&#39;http://localhost:4000/images/2015-11/Total_Arrests_Cumsum.png&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Cumulative arrests in Baltimore for 2013, 2014, and 2015.  Click image to enlarge.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
--&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;drug-related-arrests-have-continued-the-same-downward-trend-as-preceded-freddie-gray&quot;&gt;Drug-related arrests have continued the same downward trend as preceded Freddie Gray.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Former Commissioner Batts also claimed that during the unrest, enough prescription drugs from pharmacies had been stolen to “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.baltimoresun.com/news/maryland/baltimore-riots/bal-drugs-on-baltimore-streets-could-keep-it-high-for-a-year-batts-says-20150604-story.html&quot;&gt;keep Baltimore high for a year&lt;/a&gt;.”  If that were the case, I’d expect our police force to up their game and target known drug havens, resulting in more arrests.  That hasn’t happened, though.  In fact, the proportion of controlled dangerous substance charges as a proportion of total arrests has actually continued the same downward trend from the previous two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Percent weekly arrests that are CDS-related, Baltimore in 2015.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015-11/Percent_Weekly_CDS.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!--
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#39;http://localhost:4000/images/2015-11/Percent_Weekly_CDS.png&#39;&gt;&lt;img src=&#39;http://localhost:4000/images/2015-11/Percent_Weekly_CDS.png&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Percent weekly arrests that are CDS-related, Baltimore in 2015.  Click image to enlarge.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
--&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;baltimore-police-focused-entirely-on-curfew-violations-during-the-week-following-the-riots&quot;&gt;Baltimore Police focused &lt;em&gt;entirely&lt;/em&gt; on curfew violations during the week following the riots.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The total weekly arrests dropped dramatically in the weeks following the Freddie Gray unrest.  The head of the FOP said that cops were &lt;a href=&quot;http://baltimore.cbslocal.com/2015/06/02/commissioner-batts-stolen-prescription-drugs-partly-to-blame-for-surge-in-violence/&quot;&gt;“more hesitant” but that there was not a “slowdown”&lt;/a&gt; (a claim Former Commissioner Batts &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thedailybeast.com/cheats/2015/09/03/ex-baltimore-top-cop-admits-to-slowdown.html&quot;&gt;later reversed&lt;/a&gt;).  This always sounded to me like a contradiction in terms: if someone is more hesitant to do something, they are less likely to do it.  We now know there was a slowdown, but it didn’t come until after officers were charged.  What were they up to prior to that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Top 5 charges before and after Monday, April 27 unrest.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015-11/Top5_Arrest_Counts.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#39;http://localhost:4000/images/2015-11/Top5_Arrest_Counts.png&#39;&gt;&lt;img src=&#39;http://localhost:4000/images/2015-11/Top5_Arrest_Counts.png&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Top 5 charges before and after Monday, April 27 unrest.  Click image to enlarge.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt; --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the week immediately following the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.motherjones.com/politics/2015/04/how-baltimore-riots-began-mondawmin-purge&quot;&gt;police-induced rioting on Monday, April 27&lt;/a&gt;, cops were entirely focused on curfew violations.  It wasn’t until after that week that we saw the drop in total arrests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;besides-homicides-first-degree-assaults-and-gun-related-offenses-have-relatedly-increased&quot;&gt;Besides homicides, first degree assaults and gun-related offenses have relatedly increased.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much has been made of the increase in violence since the summer.  Indeed first degree assaults and gun-related offenses both increased over the summer and remain elevated compared to earlier in the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Percent of weekly arrests that are gun-related.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015-11/Percent_Weekly_Guns.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;width: 100%; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;

All data, including BPD arrests and city employee payrolls, obtained from &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.baltimorecity.gov/&quot;&gt;Open Baltimore&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;

Analysis conducted using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.python.org&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandas.pydata.org&quot;&gt;Pandas&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.plot.ly&quot;&gt;Plot.ly&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;

Full analysis IPython notebook can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jtelszasz/baltimore_crime/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  (function(i,s,o,g,r,a,m){i[&#39;GoogleAnalyticsObject&#39;]=r;i[r]=i[r]||function(){
  (i[r].q=i[r].q||[]).push(arguments)},i[r].l=1*new Date();a=s.createElement(o),
  m=s.getElementsByTagName(o)[0];a.async=1;a.src=g;m.parentNode.insertBefore(a,m)
  })(window,document,&#39;script&#39;,&#39;//www.google-analytics.com/analytics.js&#39;,&#39;ga&#39;);

  ga(&#39;create&#39;, &#39;UA-58835878-1&#39;, &#39;auto&#39;);
  ga(&#39;send&#39;, &#39;pageview&#39;);

&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/15/Policing-In-Baltimore-In-2015</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/15/Policing-In-Baltimore-In-2015</guid>
        
        <category>Baltimore</category>
        
        <category>crime</category>
        
        <category>police</category>
        
        <category>open-data</category>
        
        <category>FreddieGray</category>
        
        
        <category>open data</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What I&#39;m Up To</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Just a quick note to highlight some recent publicity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June, Technical.ly was kind enough to again shine a light on some of my analysis, this time &lt;a href=&quot;http://technical.ly/baltimore/2015/06/04/baltimore-blight-maps-ouazad-elszasz/&quot;&gt;on vacant buildings and lots in Baltimore&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://plot.ly&quot;&gt;Plot.ly&lt;/a&gt; also &lt;a href=&quot;https://plot.ly/ipython-notebooks/baltimore-vital-signs/&quot;&gt;used my iPython notebook&lt;/a&gt; for my &lt;a href=&quot;http://bniajfi.org/&quot;&gt;Baltimore Vital Signs&lt;/a&gt; analysis as an example of how to use the tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This past Friday I participated in &lt;a href=&quot;http://bniajfi.org/data_day/2015agenda/&quot;&gt;Baltimore Data Day&lt;/a&gt; hosted by &lt;a href=&quot;http://bniajfi.org/&quot;&gt;Baltimore Neighborhood Indicators Alliance&lt;/a&gt; at University of Baltimore.  I was invited to contribute to a panel on civic technology and I sincerely hope someone, anyone, in the room gained something from it.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://technical.ly/baltimore/2015/07/13/data-day-crime-data-bmoremapped-training-set/&quot;&gt;Technical.ly&lt;/a&gt; has a quick blurb about it as well as my quick glance at Baltimore police arrest data post-Freddie Gray.  Also be sure to check out Ryan Smith’s map work &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bmoremapped.com/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and stay tuned for his new crime map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coming up July 28&lt;/strong&gt;, I’ll be at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/Transportation-Techies/events/222183536/&quot;&gt;DC Transportation Techies meetup&lt;/a&gt; which is making a cameo in Baltimore at the Hyatt Regency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve added all this stuff to &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/The-Work&quot;&gt;The Work&lt;/a&gt; page (upper left corner) as well as my slide deck from my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/Baltimore-Civic-Hacking-Meetup/events/222166589/&quot;&gt;“Apps Are Not The Answer”&lt;/a&gt; talk at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hackbaltimore.org&quot;&gt;Hack Baltimore&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  (function(i,s,o,g,r,a,m){i[&#39;GoogleAnalyticsObject&#39;]=r;i[r]=i[r]||function(){
  (i[r].q=i[r].q||[]).push(arguments)},i[r].l=1*new Date();a=s.createElement(o),
  m=s.getElementsByTagName(o)[0];a.async=1;a.src=g;m.parentNode.insertBefore(a,m)
  })(window,document,&#39;script&#39;,&#39;//www.google-analytics.com/analytics.js&#39;,&#39;ga&#39;);

  ga(&#39;create&#39;, &#39;UA-58835878-1&#39;, &#39;auto&#39;);
  ga(&#39;send&#39;, &#39;pageview&#39;);

&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/15/What-Im-Up-To</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/15/What-Im-Up-To</guid>
        
        <category>open-data</category>
        
        <category>transportation</category>
        
        <category>civic-tech</category>
        
        <category>apps</category>
        
        
        <category>articles</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Arrests in Baltimore Drop in May</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There’s been quite a bit of discussion about whether or not protests regarding police brutality have made it less likely that police are willing to do the hard work necessary to enforce the law and fight crime.  &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter which camp you’re in, it’s clear (at least as far as the published data are concerned) that &lt;a href=&quot;http://http://www.nytimes.com/2015/06/13/us/after-freddie-gray-death-west-baltimores-police-presence-drops-and-murders-soar.html?smid=tw-share&amp;amp;_r=0&quot;&gt;arrests have taken a dive in Baltimore&lt;/a&gt;.  Police Commissioner Batts can dodge or deflect all he wants, but as has been reported, arrests have dropped and the city data corroborate it.  Total arrests in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.baltimorecity.gov&quot;&gt;Open Baltimore&lt;/a&gt; data for April 2015 were 2,438 while in May there were 1,449, a drop of about 40%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;fullwidth&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015-06/baltimore_daily_arrest_count_around_FG.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having the granular arrest data for Baltimore we can also take a look at whether or not the decline in arrests was more pronounced in particular areas (like West Baltimore, as the NY Times article linked above describes).  At first glance a lot (around 45%) of arrest records are not geocoded with a lat-long pair and without knowing the reason for this exclusion it’s a safer assumption that there is some bias in the data available.  Stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;fullwidth&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015-06/baltimore_2015_weekly_arrest_count_thru_may.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data obtained from &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.baltimorecity.gov/&quot;&gt;Open Baltimore&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Analysis conducted using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.python.org&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandas.pydata.org&quot;&gt;Pandas&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.plot.ly&quot;&gt;Plot.ly&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Full analysis IPython notebook can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jtelszasz/baltimore_crime/blob/master/post_freddiegray_crime.ipynb&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  (function(i,s,o,g,r,a,m){i[&#39;GoogleAnalyticsObject&#39;]=r;i[r]=i[r]||function(){
  (i[r].q=i[r].q||[]).push(arguments)},i[r].l=1*new Date();a=s.createElement(o),
  m=s.getElementsByTagName(o)[0];a.async=1;a.src=g;m.parentNode.insertBefore(a,m)
  })(window,document,&#39;script&#39;,&#39;//www.google-analytics.com/analytics.js&#39;,&#39;ga&#39;);

  ga(&#39;create&#39;, &#39;UA-58835878-1&#39;, &#39;auto&#39;);
  ga(&#39;send&#39;, &#39;pageview&#39;);

&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/15/Arrests-In-Baltimore-Drop-In-May</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/15/Arrests-In-Baltimore-Drop-In-May</guid>
        
        <category>Baltimore</category>
        
        <category>open-data</category>
        
        <category>police</category>
        
        <category>FreddieGray</category>
        
        
        <category>articles</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>B&#39;More Schools Surrounded by Blight and Danger</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Many small and midsize American cities have experienced decades of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shrinking_cities_in_the_United_States&quot;&gt;population shrinkage&lt;/a&gt;, but as you can imagine, it’s not so easy to shrink the physical footprint of a city.   Compound this with the housing bubble burst a few years ago and significant wealth inequality and it’s no surprise that so many cities are wrestling with blight and abandonment.  Even though &lt;a href=&quot;http://articles.baltimoresun.com/2011-12-06/news/bs-md-ci-srb-looks-ahead-20111202_1_mayor-stephanie-rawlings-blake-property-tax-rate-half-century-of-population-decline&quot;&gt;SRB wants to bring in 10,000 new families&lt;/a&gt;, there’s little chance the vacant property issue in Baltimore is going away anytime soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the safety hazard neglected structures can pose, vacant lots and buildings are magnets for &lt;a href=&quot;http://articles.chicagotribune.com/1992-02-10/news/9201130233_1_vacant-buildings-abandoned-demolishes&quot;&gt;serious&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://articles.baltimoresun.com/2014-08-07/news/bs-crime-vacants-20140806_1_property-crime-serious-crime-violent-crime&quot;&gt;crime&lt;/a&gt;, including &lt;em&gt;gang activity, drugs, murder, assault, and rape&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to get a look at how blight is affecting Baltimore one pretty straightforward exercise is to map all of these abandoned buildings and parcels to see what the city looks like.  I did this in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/articles/Baltimore-Vacant-Houses-On-Citylab/&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, and this work has been &lt;a href=&quot;http://technical.ly/baltimore/2012/08/09/15928-vacant-buildings-baltimore-city-map/&quot;&gt;done before&lt;/a&gt;.  It should come as no surprise to anyone living in Baltimore where the neighborhoods hardest hit with blight are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But context is everything, and the story these data tells us about what it’s like to be a school-aged kid in Baltimore is harrowing. &lt;strong&gt;The analysis suggests that about 68% of all vacant buildings in Baltimore are within a quarter mile of a city school, while about 27% of all vacant parcel area is within the same distance.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below you’ll see just how rampant this issue is for children in Baltimore.  The map shows a quarter-mile radius around each city school and the vacant parcels (blue) and vacant buildings (orange) within those buffers (data from &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.baltimorecity.gov&quot;&gt;Open Baltimore&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;width:90%;&quot;&gt;  
&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;520&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;https://jtelszasz.cartodb.com/viz/8d52d710-4ffc-11e5-b7d9-0e018d66dc29/embed_map&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The school with the most vacant buildings within a quarter mile is an &lt;strong&gt;elementary&lt;/strong&gt; school - Roots and Branches School - with a whopping &lt;strong&gt;722 vacant buildings surrounding it&lt;/strong&gt;. Unfortunately it shouldn’t come as a surprise that it’s in West Baltimore, just a few blocks south of where Freddie Gray lived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the same data without the geospatial information and plotted for comparison and trends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&#39;https://plot.ly/~jtelszasz/261/&#39;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;   --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;50%&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://plot.ly/~jtelszasz/261.embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://plot.ly/~jtelszasz/261/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Baltimore City Schools Surrounded by Blight&quot; style=&quot;display: block; text-align: left;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://plot.ly/~jtelszasz/261.png&quot; alt=&quot;Baltimore City Schools Surrounded by Blight&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; onerror=&quot;this.onerror=null;this.src=&#39;https://plot.ly/404.png&#39;;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;script data-plotly=&quot;jtelszasz:261&quot; src=&quot;https://plot.ly/embed.js&quot; async&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; --&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-opportunity&quot;&gt;An opportunity?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The obvious concern is the exposure of children to serious hazards in and around these lots and buildings, and based on the numbers this is nothing short of &lt;strong&gt;an emergency&lt;/strong&gt; of the highest order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’d like to suggest that with a little bit of ingenuity this presents an opportunity as well.  What if the city just handed over some of these lots and buildings to schools?  What could they do with them?  Of course abandoned structures would need to undergo inspection and clean up first.  Some schools obviously might be closer to more ideal structures while others might be closer to more open parcels of land that they could take over.  Obviously this would hardly put a dent in the approximately 17,000 vacant buildings in Baltimore, but at least we’d be doing something with a few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this could become an interesting study in urban planning, with multiple layers from the city-system scale down to the architectural-site scale.  I’m envisioning a network of nodes made up of school-affiliated parcels and structures that provide a rich learning network.  Students could visit each other’s sites and learn and exchange ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a few ideas I’ve had are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Greenhouses, gardens, or urban ecology/farming.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Renewable energy generation.  (Maybe a next step in analysis is solar or wind potential modeling?)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;High school shop class/Habitat for Humanity collaboration for rebuilding and construction.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Urban art classes: graffiti, sculpture, etc. (My personal favorite.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Parks, playgrounds, basketball courts, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Invite the students to devise their own plans should they be given a plot of land or building.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;width: 100%; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;

Data obtained from &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.baltimorecity.gov/&quot;&gt;Open Baltimore&lt;/a&gt; and the&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bniajfi.org/indicators&quot;&gt; Baltimore Neighborhoods Indicators Alliance - Jacob France Institute.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Analysis conducted using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.python.org&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandas.pydata.org&quot;&gt;Pandas&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.plot.ly&quot;&gt;Plot.ly&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.qgis.com&quot;&gt;QGIS&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cartodb.com&quot;&gt;CartoDB&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;

Analysis files including any iPython notebooks can be found on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jtelszasz/baltimore-schools-blight&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  (function(i,s,o,g,r,a,m){i[&#39;GoogleAnalyticsObject&#39;]=r;i[r]=i[r]||function(){
  (i[r].q=i[r].q||[]).push(arguments)},i[r].l=1*new Date();a=s.createElement(o),
  m=s.getElementsByTagName(o)[0];a.async=1;a.src=g;m.parentNode.insertBefore(a,m)
  })(window,document,&#39;script&#39;,&#39;//www.google-analytics.com/analytics.js&#39;,&#39;ga&#39;);

  ga(&#39;create&#39;, &#39;UA-58835878-1&#39;, &#39;auto&#39;);
  ga(&#39;send&#39;, &#39;pageview&#39;);

&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/15/Vacant-Lots-and-Bldgs-Near-Schools</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/15/Vacant-Lots-and-Bldgs-Near-Schools</guid>
        
        <category>Baltimore</category>
        
        <category>cities</category>
        
        <category>buildings</category>
        
        <category>schools</category>
        
        <category>urban-planning</category>
        
        
        <category>articles</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Baltimore Vacant Housing on The Atlantic&#39;s Citylab</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.citylab.com/housing/2015/05/mapping-the-density-of-baltimores-vacant-housing-crisis/394196/&quot;&gt;Citylab from The Atlantic&lt;/a&gt; just bounced &lt;a href=&quot;https://citiesblogger.wordpress.com/2015/05/27/the-urban-blight-that-is-baltimores-inner-city/&quot;&gt;some work done&lt;/a&gt; by an economist named Amine Ouazad that maps the density of vacant housing in Baltimore.  The data Ouazad used are from the American Community Survey from the U.S. Census Bureau and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ouazad.com/Maps/Baltimore_Vacancies/index.html&quot;&gt;this is the resulting map&lt;/a&gt;.  Coincidently I had already been working with &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.baltimorecity.gov&quot;&gt;Open Baltimore’s&lt;/a&gt;vacant building and lot data for a different analysis but I figured I could quickly respond to Ouazad’s map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it’s an artifact of the data used and the census tract samples, but a similar plot using data from &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.baltimorecity.gov&quot;&gt;Open Baltimore&lt;/a&gt; shows more clearly the divides within the city.  One commenter named “Jack” on the Citylab post indicated that the map showed high concentrations basically throughout the city, including wealthier and more business-centric neighborhoods like Mt. Vernon/Belvedere, Inner Harbor, Canton, and Federal Hill - comprising what we in Baltimore like to call &lt;a href=&quot;http://thebaltimorechop.com/tag/the-white-l/&quot;&gt;“The White L.”&lt;/a&gt;  On first glance at the Ouazad map my intuition agreed with Jack, and here’s what the Open Baltimore data actually look like.  There are two layers - a heat map and the actual vacant building footprints (in black) so when you zoom in you can see the actual vacant buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;90%&quot; height=&quot;520&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;https://jtelszasz.cartodb.com/viz/26254996-084f-11e5-b31b-0e018d66dc29/embed_map&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data obtained from &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.baltimorecity.gov/&quot;&gt;Open Baltimore&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Plots obtained using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.python.org&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandas.pydata.org&quot;&gt;Pandas&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.qgis.com&quot;&gt;QGIS&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cartodb.com&quot;&gt;Carto.db&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  (function(i,s,o,g,r,a,m){i[&#39;GoogleAnalyticsObject&#39;]=r;i[r]=i[r]||function(){
  (i[r].q=i[r].q||[]).push(arguments)},i[r].l=1*new Date();a=s.createElement(o),
  m=s.getElementsByTagName(o)[0];a.async=1;a.src=g;m.parentNode.insertBefore(a,m)
  })(window,document,&#39;script&#39;,&#39;//www.google-analytics.com/analytics.js&#39;,&#39;ga&#39;);

  ga(&#39;create&#39;, &#39;UA-58835878-1&#39;, &#39;auto&#39;);
  ga(&#39;send&#39;, &#39;pageview&#39;);

&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/15/Baltimore-Vacant-Houses-On-Citylab</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/15/Baltimore-Vacant-Houses-On-Citylab</guid>
        
        <category>Baltimore</category>
        
        <category>cities</category>
        
        <category>buildings</category>
        
        <category>urban-planning</category>
        
        
        <category>articles</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Verizon Wireless Cost Estimation</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, my 2-year contract came due for a phone upgrade.  Seeing as how I was on an iPhone 4 and Apple’s recent OS upgrades have sucked the life clean out of it, I was looking forward to purchasing a new phone with the hopes that the new one will last beyond the 2-year cycle.  I was going to purchase an iPhone 6, and I knew (or so I thought) what it would cost up front if I were to sign on a new 2-year contract.  Simple, straight-forward.  No sales pitches necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I entered the Verizon Wireless store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within a few moments of arrival and signing in, my name was called and I was paired with a sales rep.  Whilst hovering over me, he quickly moved the conversation from the phone itself to something called the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.verizonwireless.com/support/verizon-edge-faqs/&quot;&gt;Edge plan&lt;/a&gt;.  I hadn’t bothered looking at the Edge plan before coming to the store - from the marketing material it seemed that it was targeted at customers interested in upgrading their phone more rapidly than every two years.  I do not count myself in that category, so I didn’t bother looking into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The salesman threw so many numbers at me that my head was spinning.  He was claiming that I could get some accessory package essentially for free by switching to the Edge program.  I couldn’t follow any of his logic, and I was only marginally clearer on the details when the manager attempted to explain the costs to me.  I walked out of the store frustrated and not wanting to commit there and then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I figure I can’t have been the only Verizon customer to have experienced this recently.  In order to figure out what the actual costs were and whether I’d actually save money I made a quick calculator for my family and I to use.  I’m sharing it here in case it helps others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s pretty simple for now, and assumes you aren’t taking the bait and trying to upgrade your phone more frequently than two years.  The white boxes are entry cells: select the phone you want, enter your typical monthly service costs, and enter the percent down payment on the phone you’d like to make if you’re considering the Edge program.  The box to the right gives your estimated monthly bill (bold black text) and the total cost over two years for your options (in bold red text).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1uHdFLi_sEbyXN573mBUnqQPJdWCfkjuve-smumsCrXE/pubhtml?widget=true&amp;amp;headers=false&quot; width=&quot;90%&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  (function(i,s,o,g,r,a,m){i[&#39;GoogleAnalyticsObject&#39;]=r;i[r]=i[r]||function(){
  (i[r].q=i[r].q||[]).push(arguments)},i[r].l=1*new Date();a=s.createElement(o),
  m=s.getElementsByTagName(o)[0];a.async=1;a.src=g;m.parentNode.insertBefore(a,m)
  })(window,document,&#39;script&#39;,&#39;//www.google-analytics.com/analytics.js&#39;,&#39;ga&#39;);

  ga(&#39;create&#39;, &#39;UA-58835878-1&#39;, &#39;auto&#39;);
  ga(&#39;send&#39;, &#39;pageview&#39;);

&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/15/Verizon-Wireless-Calculator</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/15/Verizon-Wireless-Calculator</guid>
        
        <category>Verizon</category>
        
        <category>smart-phones</category>
        
        
        <category>articles</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
